within a year of the Gezi protests with comfortable margins. To be sure, governments have different resources to bring to the table. It's not the same game, but the differences are instructive. And like all such stories, this is not a story just of technology. It's what technology allows us to do converging with what we want to do. Today's social movements want to operate informally. They do not want institutional leadership. They want to stay out of politics because they fear corruption and cooptation. They have a point. Modern representative democracies are being strangled in many countries by powerful interests. But operating this way makes it hard for them to sustain over the long term and exert leverage over the system, which leads to frustrated protesters dropping out, and even more corrupt politics. And politics and democracy without an effective challenge hobbles, because the causes that have inspired the modern recent movements are crucial. Climate change is barreling towards us. Inequality is stifling human growth and potential and economies. Authoritarianism is choking many countries. We need movements to be more effective. Now, some people have argued that the problem is today's movements are not formed of people who take as many risks as before, and that is not true. From Gezi to Tahrir to elsewhere, I've seen people put their lives and livelihoods on the line. It's also not true, as Malcolm Gladwell claimed, that today's protesters form weaker virtual ties. No, they come to these protests, just like before, with their friends, existing networks, and sometimes they do make new friends for life. I still see the friends that I made in those Zapatista-convened global protests more than a decade ago, and the bonds between strangers are not worthless. When I got tear-gassed in Gezi, people I didn't know helped me and one another instead of running away. In Tahrir, I saw people, protesters, working really hard to keep each other safe and protected. And digital awareness-raising is great, because changing minds is the bedrock of changing politics. But movements today have to move beyond participation at great scale very fast and figure out how to think together collectively, develop strong policy proposals, create consensus, figure out the political steps and relate them to leverage, because all these good intentions and bravery and sacrifice by itself are not going to be enough. And there are many efforts. In New Zealand, a group of young people are developing a platform called Loomio for participatory decision making at scale. In Turkey, 140Journos are holding hack-a-thons so that they support communities as well as citizen journalism. In Argentina, an open-source platform called DemocracyOS is bringing participation to parliaments and political parties. These are all great, and we need more, but the answer won't just be better online decision-making, because to update democracy, we are going to need to innovate at every level, from the organizational to the political to the social. Because to succeed over the long term, sometimes you do need tea without sugar along with your Twitter. Thank you. (Applause)
dans l'année qui a suivi les manifestations de Gezi. Oui, les gouvernements ont différentes ressources à apporter ce n'est donc pas pareil, mais les différences sont instructives. Comme pour toutes ces histoires, il ne s'agit pas juste de technologie, mais bien de ce qu'elle nous aide à accomplir et réaliser. Les mouvements sociaux d'aujourd'hui veulent opérer de manière informelle. ils ne veulent pas d'encadrement institutionel. Ils ne veulent pas se mêler de politique par peur de corruption et cooptation. Et ils n'ont pas tort. De puissants intérêts font taire les agents de la démocratie moderne dans de nombreux pays. Mais de cette manière il leur est difficile de durer dans le temps et d'influencer le système, ce qui cause l'amenuisement des protestataires, et encore plus de corruption en politique. La politique et la démocratie sont bancales sans un recours efficace, parce que les causes qui ont inspiré les mouvements modernes sont cruciales. Le réchauffement climatique nous guette. Les inégalités étouffent la croissance humaine, notre potentiel, l'économie... L'autoritarisme étouffe de nombreux pays. Il faut que ces mouvements soient plus efficaces. Certains avancent que que le problème est qu'on ne prend pas autant de risques qu'avant. Et ce n'est simplement pas vrai. A Gezi, à Tahrir et ailleurs, j'ai vu des gens mettre leur vie en danger. Malcolm Gladwell a tort de dire que les manifestants d'aujourd'hui ont des liens virtuels moins solides. Non, ils viennent à ces manifestations, tout comme avant, avec leurs amis, leur réseau, et parfois ils forment de nouvelles amitiés à vie. Je revois encore les amis que je me suis faits lors des manifestations zapatistes il y a dix ans. Et les liens entre inconnus ne sont pas sans valeur. Quand j'ai reçu du gaz lacrymogène à Gezi, des inconnus m'ont aidée. Tout le monde s'entraidait au lieu de s'enfuir. À Tahrir, j'ai vu des gens, des protestataires, travailler vraiment dur pour se protéger les uns les autres. Et sensibiliser au numérique est génial parce qu'on change la politique en changeant les perceptions. Mais les mouvements contemporains doivent rapidement passer outre le taux de participation, et trouver un moyen de penser ensemble comme une collectivité, de développer de fortes propositions politiques, créer un consensus, de déterminer les étapes politiques, et de les comprendre pour avoir du poids, parce que toutes ces bonnes intentions, ce courage et ces sacrifices ne seront pas assez. Il y a beaucoup d'efforts. En Nouvelle-Zélande, un groupe de jeunes développe une plateforme appelée Loomio pour la prise de décision participative à une certaine échelle. En Turquie, 140 Journos conduisent un hackathon pour apporter du soutien aux communautés et au journalisme citoyen. En Argentine, une plateforme open-source du nom de DemocracyOS encourage la participation au parlement et aux partis politiques. Tout ceci est génial et il nous en faut plus. Mais il nous faut plus qu'un meilleur processus décisionnel en ligne. Pour actualiser la démocratie, il nous faudra innover à tous les niveaux. De l'organisationnel au politique, au social. Car pour obtenir un succès à long terme, parfois, il est bon de prendre du thé sans sucre, pour accompagner nos Tweets. Merci. (Applaudissements)